[Music]
corporations are legally required to
maximize shareholder profits and
therefore have to oppose public health
policies that could threaten profits i
mean it's just how the system is set up
unequivocal long-standing evidence shows
that to achieve this diverse industries
with products that can damage health
have worked systematically to subvert
the scientific process
take the sugar industry for example
internal documents so that they were
concerned that health food fattis were
becoming an active menace to the
industry
sugar was under attack and many of the
poor unfortunate public swallow the
misinformation broadcast by the
propagandists
what were books like jedkins
pure white and deadly saying
all the propaganda is to the effect that
sugar is a non-essential food
no how dare they say sugar is a
non-essential food i mean next they'll
be saying it's not really food at all
and that was the sugar industries line
sugar is a cheap safe food and this
coming from the founder and chair of
harvard's nutrition department frederick
stare long known as harvard's sugar
pushing nutritionist
not only did the sugar industry try to
influence the direction of dental
research but heart disease research as
well paying steroin colleagues to write
this review to help downplay any risk
from sugar
now to be fair this was five years
before we even realized triglycerides
were also an independent risk factor
beyond just cholesterol the main reason
attention stayed focused on saturated
fat is not because of the might of the
sugar industry there was just not as
much data to support it in fact the even
more powerful meat and dairy industries
love the anti-sugar message
who do you think sponsored yudkin right
in fact on the first page of uh of pure
white and deadly he thanks all the food
and drug companies that have provided
him with constant generous support who
paid for jenkins uh speaking tour the
egg industry of course to try to take
some heat off of cholesterol
hegstad one of the co-authors of the
funded review
and wasn't exactly an industry
cheerleader he recommended people cut
down on all the risky stuff less meat
less saturated fat less cholesterol and
less sugar less salt it wasn't the sugar
industry that got him fired for speaking
truth to power it was the beef industry
the sugar industry was able to conceal
its funding because the new england
journal of medicine didn't require
disclosure of conflicts of interest
until 17 years later these muckraking
researchers suggest policymakers should
consider giving less weight to food
industry-funded studies
but why is the food industry funding
studies at all right i mean when it
comes to the corporate manipulation of
research
ultimately conflicts of interest don't
just need to be disclosed and managed
but ideally eliminated right things may
not change until public health
researchers start refusing to take money
from the junk food industry period it
worked for tobacco
many prestigious medical and public
health institutions have instituted bans
on tobacco industry funding
but wait can't scientists remain
objective and impartial even the face of
all that cash
apparently not as industry funded
research has been shown to be up to 88
times more likely to produce funder
favorable outcomes
what do we think corporations are in the
business of just handing out money for
free
the classic example is the american
academy of pediatric dentistry who
accepted a million-dollar grant from
coca-cola before the grant their
official position was that the frequent
consumption of sugary beverages can be a
significant factor in the initiation and
progression of dental cavities
which after the grant changed to
scientific evidence is certainly not
clear on the exact role the soft drinks
play
as cspi's integrity and science project
put it
what a difference a million dollars
makes
[Music]
foreign